Samuel Billings Capen collection of writings, 1882-1913.
Congregational Library & Archives
Samuel Billings Capen collection of writings, 1882-1913.
MS0835
Congregational Library & Archives
.35 Cubic Feet
(1 case)
Samuel Billings Capen was born on December 12, 1842 in Boston. Samuel would become heavily involved in a number of different organizations starting in 1882 when he became the president of the Congregational Sunday School and Publishing Society. The American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions would also benefit from Capen's services when he became president in 1899. He was a part of the Haystack Prayer Meeting in 1906 and would eventually travel to Asia as the head of the ABCFM and as a member of the World peace Foundation. He died of pneumonia in Shanghai, China on January 29, 1914. This collection contains various speeches and writings by and about Samuel Billings Capen.
Capen, Samuel B. (Samuel Billings), 1842-1914
Kehew, Mary Morton, 1859-1918
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information is available for this collection.
Biographical Information
Samuel Billings Capen was born on December 12, 1842 in Boston. Capen would graduate from Boston English High School in 1858 and would eventually become a carpet dealer under the name Torrey, Bright & Capen. Capen would also double as an active member of church and civic affairs which eventually led him to Sunday School work at the Central Congregational Church in Jamaica Plain. Samuel married his wife Helen in 1869. Capen would eventually receive his honorary A.M. degree from Dartmouth College and an L.L.D. from Oberlin College and Middlebury College.
Samuel would become heavily involved in a number of different organizations starting in 1882 when he became the president of the Congregational Sunday School and Publishing Society. He was able to reorganize the group's finances and set them up for future success. He also served on the Boston School Committee from 1888 to 1893 and was the chairman in 1893. Other organizations he was a part of include the Boston City Missionary Society, United Society of Christian Endeavor, Boston Chamber of Commerce, North American Civic League for Immigrants, Watch and Ward Society, Massachusetts Bible Society, Mayflower Society, Boston Municipal League and more.
The American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions would also benefit from Capen's services when he became president in 1899. He was a part of the Haystack Prayer Meeting in 1906 and would eventually travel to Asia as the head of the ABCFM and as a member of the World peace Foundation. He died of pneumonia in Shanghai, China on January 29, 1914.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains various speeches and writings by and about Samuel Billings Capen.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged chronologically.
Bibliography
1. "Samuel B. Capen." The Missionary Herald 110, no 3 (1914): 112-114. Accessed December 1, 2021. https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015010806365&view=1up&seq=137&q1=capen.
2. Steece, Arvel M. "Markers Along the Congregational Way." NFPA. National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: September 10, 2006. http://blog.nfpa.com/CMSUploads/24_MArkersAlongTheWay.pdf
Christian education of children.; Christianity and politics.; Speeches, addresses, etc., American.; Correspondence.; Capen, Samuel B. (Samuel Billings), 1842-1914; Ginn, Edwin, 1838-1914
- Congregational Club festival notes, May 31, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Planning, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Teaching of Morals in the Public Schools, 1888-04-01 1888-04-30; April 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Committee on manual training schools reports, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Parental school report, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles on and By Samuel Billings Capen, 1891 1899; 1891-1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- School accommodations report, 1892-01-01 1892-01-31; January 1892 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Municipal League invitation, November 2, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The International Evangel, June 24, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Patriotic Aspects of the Work of the American Missionary Association, October 21, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Report of the Congregational Club in regard to the International Council, October 23, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 86th Annual Report of the Boston Children's Friend Society, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter to Samuel Billings Capen, October 20, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 184th report of the Massachusetts Bible Society, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence between Mary Kehew and Samuel Billings Capen, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter to Samuel Billings Capen and Edwin Ginn, August 15, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Someone is shriveling, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Duties of American Citizenship, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Christian Endeavor Civic Clubs, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Someone is shirking, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- The Sunday School Offering, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Notable Public School Service, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Memorial Address, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Writings related to Samuel Billings Capen, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Scope and Contents
  This folder contains items which discuss or mention Samuel Billings Capen, but it cannot be determined if any were by Capen himself.